hello and welcome everyone it's December
31st 2022 we are here in the 2022 active
inference live stream review
welcome to the active inference
Institute we're a participatory online
Institute that is communicating learning
and practicing applied active inference
this is a recorded and an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome we'll be following good video
etiquette for live streams
head over to
activeinference.org to learn more about
getting involved in live streams or
various other projects and learning
groups at The Institute
well today is going to be great and fun
we are simply reviewing our streams from
this past year we're going to touch
lightly or mildly on all the streams
that we carried out from 2022 and
by way of doing that we may end up
reflecting and preflecting thinking
about where we're going to head in 2023
so we'll begin with just an introduction
and a hello
I'm Daniel I am a researcher in
California and I'm excited to reflect
this is like the dot zero
uh preparation dot 1.2 discussion and
then afterwards we reflect this is like
the book and reflection for all of those
and so it's like an even deeper level of
nesting when we're going to juxtapose so
many things that we talked about
and I'm sure at some neural level
whether somebody was familiar with the
streams or whether they listen to none
of them there's going to be something
about just touching on so many topics
and so many perspectives being
juxtaposed that I think is going to be
really Pleasant
to you Dean
yeah thanks Dan I'm Dean I'm here in
Calgary um maybe I'm a revised or a
recycled researcher I don't know what my
title is now but
um after Daniel
said hey I think we should do this again
I was like yeah we absolutely should
because it's
my metaphor is that it's kind of like
double double frying those french fries
it's uh it just adds an an extra layer
of integration or crispiness that's uh
hard to resist you you get a because the
way that we present these things is is
hopefully a way of integrating a bunch
of information because we Talk Amongst
ourselves and it's helpful and then you
look back at yourself talking about
yourself and others and you just get a
whole different perspective on it so I
actually am really looking forward to
sort of running through these things
it's going to be a Sprint but that's
okay it still gives you a chance to
figure out what the Milestones were it's
like seeing the entire Tour de France in
in 30 SEC or 30 minutes which is kind of
fun
it's like we completed that marathon and
now we're high speed watching the
recording from our um body camera
all right well
we'll keep with some patterns from the
more paper-centric discussions like
leading with big questions so what was
our stream of attention in 2022 and
where and how will we stream in 2023
what did you have to add on these
questions
um not not a heck of a lot I mean it's
it'll be interesting given the amount of
time that you committed to the Endeavor
of here's 2022 I wonder what we'll fill
it with I'm curious now that now that
you're on the back side of that
um what parts of what you hoped would be
achieved came about and what parts do
you think are still there's still room
for some some back filling
we'll come to that after we've touched
on everything good
yeah yeah I really liked what you added
here though in a world that is becoming
more familiar with congregation and
digital mediums and spaces
is our use of Technology more than an
easy way to gain information access
you could be in the library all you want
and you won't read a book we can have
all the access to information in the
world and we won't necessarily
digest and incorporate we can have all
the generative AI in the world writing
in these amazing essays and making art
but where does that put us as
information of forager and then you
added can we turn figuring out into out
there figuring
and as more and more people start to
want to figure out active inference it's
not a Rubik's Cube on the table that
gets finished
and by putting it
um out there figuring is where active
infra ants are so I think that's really
exciting like we do have so much to
figure out
from all backgrounds and yet we want to
be out there figuring and having impact
I think that's where your background in
field research and my background in
sending people out into professional
settings
yeah they're very different but also
structurally very similar there's
there's no substitute for actually
picking yourself up
and it's a form of migration I don't you
like you use the word Stingray until I
can actually figure out what my
pheromone Trail is I'll I'll let you
have that piece of it but I mean I I
understand it I get it and uh
yeah
let's see where it takes us all right
roadmap
so maybe we should have done like a a uh
a rear view mirror or something but we
had 87 streams in 2022 the live streams
table has 87 rows so it was an amazing
year and the numbers are shown here
we're going to touch pretty lightly on
all of the streams
from two through nine
the round table Symposium math stream or
extreme Twitter spaces guest stream
model stream and bookstream and then
we're going to slow down a little bit
and talk about some of the papers that
we discussed
so first the overall review though
for a general Institute level review
check out our quarterly Round Table
number four so that's where we talk more
about the institute's directions other
projects and learning groups but today
we're just going to talk about the live
streams
all right what
did you write with these questions yeah
I'm I'm often curious because when
you're when you're busy constructing 87
rows when when you reached whatever that
limit is
um is there a big picture that has come
about as a result of that stack
um again it'll probably be something
we'll be able to answer better at the
conclusion of our of our chat today but
I think it's something to try to keep in
mind I don't know that we can
say with certainty that your big picture
and my sense of that same picture is the
same interpretation but it's it's a good
it's a good idea
to keep a sort of a general level sense
of so did this all come together or you
know how did the live streams
intermingle with some of the guest
streams intermingle with some of the
bookstream stuff that you and um is it
Tyler and blue are looking at right now
yeah
well the links here
can all be accessed through
activeinference.org and of course one
project of no is the active inference
Journal where all of the live streams
through the incredible work of Dave
Douglas and others
get transcribed
archived and versions up on the GitHub
so that is one structural development of
the live streams
is there a big picture
it really can feel like just moving
Pebbles back and forth
and there isn't necessarily uh a vision
of what the final nest looks like
so I hope we can kind of look back on it
once we've gone through it
all right let's jump in
yeah first round tables so we have a
tradition of four quarterly round tables
at The Institute scale
the first two one will notice are active
lab quarterly roundtables and the second
or the third and the fourth are active
inference Institute roundtables because
in the middle of 2022 we had of course
our transition from being active
inference lab to active inference
Institute so here's an image meme
that we have from the fourth quarterly
round table and these roundtables the
screenshots with who's there and who
shows up but also just what we discussed
are like planting a series of flags in
the grounds and they're an absolutely
honest representation of who we were and
what we were doing then and so I really
enjoy sometimes even looking back and
seeing how things have happened so
that's not as uh scientifically or
philosophically conceptual of a live
stream series
and the information in certain ways is
out of date
because it's more of an informative
participation oriented communication but
nonetheless a great series
and also
before we head in and to avert saying
this of every single Series in the
Stream
big appreciation for those who had the
bravery and capacity to join
whether they joined repeatedly or one
time
it's been awesome and it's totally
co-created with the people who are there
in the most just
unbelievable ways
all right
to the symposium
so this was our second applied active
inference symposium
the focus was on Robotics and the first
applied active infrared Symposium in 21
was just with Carl friston it was a
one-man show and for this Symposium we
had some more elaborate developments we
had some external co-organizers in Matt
Brown and in Mark Miller
we also wanted to host a wide variety of
speakers and perspectives so we had two
four-hour sections with one two three
four five presenters in the first
session and one two three four and a
half with Briston joining in the second
session and
we saw the state of the art in active
inference being applied to robotics we
saw embodied actual robots we learned
about some of the theory
we saw connections to previous lineages
of Robotics and also more General
control theoretic areas
each of the sessions closed with a
Roundtable discussion
the second one being more populous than
the first
and when people say like
okay enough about what active inference
is how and where can it be applied and
people commonly point to areas like
human health as well as robotics as some
of the leading areas in the recent and
in the coming years and I'm just really
happy that we were able to highlight
the state-of-the-art like this is what
Robotics and active inference looked
like in 2022 publish a transcript make
it citable and get visibility across
these different sectors so that they
could connect on some of their
developments and also their ongoing
challenges
math stream yeah go ahead good I hope
that that uh
at some point and I don't know timing
really matters but I hope at some point
people in other more dedicated learning
spaces like formal education spaces
systems
will find themselves asking questions
around how things that we've been
talking about and we've been interacting
on might
complement the way that things happen in
those systems so it's not let's go build
a robot that does X it's actually taking
the active and the fur the inferred and
taking actions on hidden States
um as a complement to
you know we've got to get a certain
score on an SAT
and I think it would be very interesting
to see when that
that
um coming together on the horizon we
know that the train tracks remain
parallel but as we look at that there's
a name for that you probably know what
it is but when it when it reaches that
Horizon it appears they've come together
and so I'm hoping that um that isn't
sort of Lost in some of these uh other
initiatives
that I know
would actually be
easier to do because there isn't such a
history and and a whole a whole bunch of
people who are very invested in
maintaining the status quo as opposed to
really journeying in ways that are um
not discarding what we know taking the
priors and allowing for some new
priorities so I just want to kind of
toss that in there
awesome thank you
we had just one math stream
formally
with David Spivak and blue facilitating
on category Theory
this is
a few train stops away
for some of us individually and for the
field but this year there have been some
incredible advances in active inference
and category Theory so the field is
being fertilized and prepared
for an incredible regenerative category
theoretic implementation of active
inference but that's all we'll say for
now here
in the OR extremes we focus on the
intersection of active inference and
organizations we had two streams
first one was with Eugene Leventhal from
the smart contract Research Forum and
the second stream was with bishan hesri
whose book governing continuous
transformation is also the focus of the
bookstream which we'll get to in a
second
and
both of these were awesome streams
there are hidden States for both
all only say what I'll say which is that
they both were incredibly informative
and the triangulation of active
inference for both of them
was something that was incredibly
natural
um coming from as in bijan's case
somebody with Decades of executive
experience who completed his PhD
dissertation on free energy governance
and sees the framework specifically
as a vehicle for moving the frontier of
leadership in organizations or Eugene
who's
um fluency with internal and external
organization
made it a natural and enjoyable
conversation and we connected a lot of
topics of interest in online and web 3
organization
so it was a great time
yes that if you uh you want to do
something interesting watch the work
screen with um and then watch the live
stream series number 36 about modeling
ourselves
and you'll very quickly see that um
Bijan was closer to the end of the year
but we were many of the things that he
spoke of we were talking about in detail
with one of the papers that we took up
basically a year ago and that's the
interesting that you can't you don't
realize that until you're on a day like
today
awesome
we had one Twitter spaces the title was
can web 3 survive without cognitive
modeling it was a provocative click bait
headline
and we had a chance on this discussion
to talk about the active block fronts
project with Jacob here as one of the
primary developers and Advocates and
stewards of that project and we
discussed this question which is can web
3 or cyber physical systems more broadly
exist in an increasingly complex present
and future without something like
cognitive modeling
for which we believe active inference is
the most composable and flexible
generalizable and Powerful framework so
I forget whether it's never ask a
question in the headline if the answer
is yes or no I I always forget so I
never know so I always approach those
headline based questions with an open
mind but
we had a good time in this discussion
and these kinds of informal formats
might have a lot of applicability we
didn't really need to prepare much there
also weren't any slides so for those who
are interested in this genre
of social audio or whatever it is called
there's a lot of opportunities for
frankly just interacting with people
where they are
talking about active inference and
making the compromise in the improvised
moment
all right
we had
quite a handful of guest streams from
number 14 to number 31. so I'm going to
just briefly try to recall and mention
those who joint
Jorge estvest discussed osteopathy and
mental health in a 14. Bobby azarian in
15.1 and 0.2 discussed Universal
bayesianism
Mark somes joined for 16 discussing
Consciousness as Precision optimization
which also was published by the active
inference journal in one of the most
manually crafted and beautiful
Publications
spoke in guest room 17 about epistemic
communities under active inference which
is a area of increasing importance
Ian Robertson Michael Kirchoff and
Julian kiverstein discussed the literal
literalist fallacy and the free energy
principle
where that was only in March it was on
Pi Day
and we uh reawakened the Kraken of the
realism instrumentalism dialectic which
I know that we're going to touch on
today again
19 Markov action discussed extended
predictive Minds
in guest stream 20 Shannon proach
discussed coordination dynamics of
multi-agent interaction and the
screenshot on the bottom left is showing
a slide from her presentation I think it
was an amazing presentation it's very
accessible and very Cutting Edge work on
multi-agent active inference
and also in the very fun setting of
music listening and creation so it was
very engaging
Adam saffron in guest room 21
discuss free will
Anna Lemke in guest room 22 discussed
dopamine Nation
and that's a fun one to view and share
because Anna comes from a Psychiatry
background not familiar with active
inference too much but
open-hearted open-minded and engaged
with real people and with research every
day so we had a really affable
conversation
in guest room 23. Maxwell ramstead and
Dalton's octavit DeVille joined for
rebooting the free energy principle
literature which was a paper
discussed that was not the title of a
paper but a paper was discussed that got
folded into the pre-play for livestream
49 so we'll talk more about Bayesian
physics then
Stephen grossberg joined for guest room
24 explainable and reliable AI
and also a commendation there to Ali who
did incredible preparation and
facilitation as well as editing the
transcript here and made this an
incredibly high quality experience for
everybody
guest room 25 Brett Anderson discussed
the Continuum of traits between Autism
and schizotyping so that was kind of
interesting work and uh speaks to a lot
of areas of meaning
in guest room 26 along with my
colleagues at Common Sense makers daphna
Shahaf Lauren Hebert Ronan tamari and
William Fisher we discussed from users
to sense makers and about stigmergy
which is collective behavioral
algorithms that modify the environment
in the context of sense making online
guest stream 27 was with John verviki
and we had a great time we had a stool
with three legs predictive processing
relevance realization active inference
and Dean and I were preparing those
slides
we had the stool going and then we
flipped the stool and it was upside down
and then that was just one of many
inversions and Transformations and John
has a very delightful and mindful way of
approaching dialogue as those who are
familiar with his work no and so we had
a great time
in 28 Giovanni Rolla discussed
reconceiving rationality and inactive
cognition
guest room 29 Shauna Dobson on making up
our minds imaginative deconstruction in
math art
for those who are looking for the Triple
Play of math art and philosophy
there is only one unicorn in this Forest
guest room 30 with keratinetrates was on
the human governance problem complex
systems and the limits of human
cognition this was a very fascinating
presentation of an artificial
intelligence system that was churning in
the background while we had a discussion
and so it was quite visually and
conceptually
interesting
and then most recently in guest room 31
Brett Kagan and Adil razi discussed
biological and synthetic intelligence
from the free energy principle
perspective and some of their empirical
work with neurons in a dish playing
video games and the way that they were
modeling that with active inference so
we had
a great set of guest streams and we look
forward to a diverse and
comprehensive set for 2023 so if you
want to join for a guest stream or if
you want to recommend or introduce
somebody this is very low bar
it can be a presentation they've given
somewhere else
some of these presenters requested us to
do background which we're happy to do
prepare questions others just show up so
if you think there's somebody who could
fit in well in a guest stream even if
they're not like in the center of the
active inference research development's
ongoing we can absolutely make it happen
15 what would you add on the guest
stream angle
well if I could if I could invite
people out myself at the same table and
I could get Dalton and I could get
Shauna yourself
and John vervacci and me just sitting
around and just talking about stuff I
think
I probably would be about as good as it
gets I think that would be just one of
the most amazing dialogues and improv
you wouldn't know where it was going to
go and that would be half the excitement
is just
people who
who can who can basically have a
conversation with anybody about topics
that are incredibly sophisticated and
yet seem to be able to bring it to a
level where as you said it's engaging
it's uh
it's really it's amazing and this is not
to downplay all the other guests that
were kind enough to to join but
again if if I were to
if I were to uh do something on a social
level on an informal level I all of
these people thank you all to all of
them
great
all right in the model streams we like
to highlight
modeling and we had three
absolutely Cutting Edge presentations
with interactive components
model Stream 5 with Pietro masaglia and
Tim ferbellen we discussed contrast of
active inference which uses some current
threads in non-active inference machine
learning like contrast of learning and
brought it into the context of active
inference to facilitate learning in
noisy environments
in model stream 6 teal field Champion
joined to discuss is quite prolific and
creative Avenue of research into
branching time active inference and
Jacob and Ali are here also did a lot of
background to prepare
and as we entertain larger and larger
State spaces
and deeper and deeper possible Futures
with more and more and more affordances
and affordances on preferences and
affordances on affordances on
preferences these State spaces become
vast
and things that you can write down on
the back of an envelope might take all
the heat in the world with current
computers to run just like you could
write down two large numbers and
multiply them but you could look at each
number and it's just a number well you
can draw a base graph and
yet to run that base graph might be not
possible so there's a lot of relevance
in this area of research of finding out
these computational acceleration methods
and heuristics
as well as even just qualitatively this
idea of branching time branching and
pruning time and what kinds of
strategies are used to branch and prune
time adaptively it's very exciting and
then
in model stream seven Connor Hines and
Daphne demekis joined to discuss Pi mdp
which is rapidly becoming the python
active inference implementation approach
of choice in the community
and it was great because we were able to
ask basic questions we were able to hear
about the intentions of the package and
we're going to have a DOT two in just a
couple of weeks
this is something
uh in terms of the package it's
something where more and more of our
work in the Institute is going to use
this package and the interoperability of
different generative models and
processes and simulations written in pi
mdp is going to facilitate the
accessibility rigor and applicability of
active inference so great work to all
those who are contributors on this
package and everybody who is out there
applying active inference
computationally and shared it with us
this way
all right and the last non-paper live
stream is the book stream
so the bookstream is being led by Blue
and Tyler Solberg and when they got a
hand on Bijan kesri's book governing
continuous transformation reframing the
strategy governance conversation
they jumped on it and they said how can
we do some kind of a regular series how
can we increase our accountability in
Reading understanding this book and also
make something for the community
and they said we want to do a weekly ish
book stream so we've done that for the
past several weeks and there will be
many more sessions to come including
discussions with the author so
um great initiative
and
it's keeping the
stove warm
on these topics of organizational
development
which are just absolutely Evergreen
yeah
all right
on to the paper live streams which we
don't play favorites
but we love the paper live streams
go ahead Dean start us with 35. where
were we
in January 22 when we were reading a
tale of two architectures free energy
its models and modularity by Majid Benny
I wish I could say that I looked a lot
younger
back then but I looked old back then too
um
I think a year ago we were pretty
excited because
I think it it felt as though
things could go in a number of different
directions and that we as a community
that were discussing a lot of the you
know most Cutting Edge on the sort of
bow wave of information that was coming
out of
people's research
um
it kind of felt like we weren't just
aggregating we were actually
kind of one step removed we weren't
getting too locked into any one
particular facet of this
multifaceted idea
and uh
it could it could um it could really
blossom into something like we had we
had this really what we thought was this
kind of magic Acorn or unicorn or
whatever and how it would be
viewed
um 360 some days later we didn't really
know but we also weren't afraid to kind
of test the limits that's what I felt 22
was more than anything else it was an
opportunity to test things and that
didn't mean that we were out to prove
people wrong we just wanted there was
now enough information and not a large
enough sample size that we could do some
cross-checking
and that sort of allowed the people that
were doing a cross-checking the ones
that were reading this long list of
papers a chance to kind of go huh okay
well I think I've seen that over here
but there seemed to be some hesitation
around whether that how far that rule
holds under this set of circumstances
and yada yada so
35.0 started out I've just put my notes
here as a formal treatment of what
graphical modeling can look like
I.E are dag dags are cyclists well DCM
are cycle based and for me the
introduction of the term joint
probability up to that point I'd never
heard of that expression
and we ended up using joint probability
in a lot of the papers that followed so
there was a bit of you could start
weaving Golden Threads between things
Majid who eventually joined us for this
um nothing but props for that guy for
again pulling in what are seemingly
really distal Concepts and making us
realize oh well if you do do that you
gain Insight pretty quickly
um
then we went on to 35 1 which was which
do we start with representation and or
effect both in order to model
uh so recognizing the importance of
personal information encapsulation
that everything doesn't have to be
absolute especially over different time
frames not just architectures although
that term was in the title of his paper
uh but the role of the architect someone
who is an applied structurer if there is
such a thing and the sort of arbitrary
nature of that
that's how how does it remain arbitrary
well by not being absolute a real clear
way of understanding the difference
between function and effective
connectivity that took up a lot of our
conversation uh proximal consistency
through time and introduce the
perspectives what the term perspective
swaps I didn't realize that I'd
introduced that into the conversation
then
um but yes that's where it all was
seeded was back in January almost a year
ago then 35.2 what are we trying to
trace separation and or boundedness the
answer to that as Majid clearly
concluded depends on what's available
so availability not just our regime of
attention so I thought that was an
incredible thing to bring up a year ago
do we keep that what are what that we
are the trans the tracers and the
modelers and the separators and the
bounders in the front of our minds as we
analyze situations if learning is
decided sought after effect
when does that help
does this lead to a year of holding up
when we are looking at a Target system
say active inference is subject and when
we as observers might be using active
inference in formal ways I.E or allowing
priors to not get in the way of new
insights assuming insights are a
priority for agents and I was interested
in thinking I wonder how they would be
able to get that into JS robots
right so that's an interesting thing to
me this is the Divide between being a
programmer of a robot where the priority
is learn
uh versus dictating how priors are
amassed and organized and then
inhabiting a programming or
participatory experience one where
deconstruction is adaptability until
ultimately something
called complexity dominates the
conversation in both of those situations
priors and priorities work in concert
but in the latter the humanist cased are
on opposite sides of a Markov blanket
so at least partially hidden but also
partially encapsulated we talked a lot
about duck rabbits
that are not riding to unicycles
concurrently whereas the robot might
that's an interesting difference there
and for humans riding two unicycles is
equal and complete partitioning or
encapsulation
so that's why it's hard to do
takes much training to be able to carry
that out
so that's 35s that was Majid and uh
bringing the the science and the
modeling and the abductive and
that was our conversation even though
his paper was in response to a couple of
other authors
um arguing that there's only one way
really to model
and so again lots of things grew out of
a paper that was meant as a response and
created a whole different ecosystem
awesome wow I'll just give a short
thought
graphical models and network Theory are
at the heart of active inference as well
as many other fields and what it means
to have a network or a graphical model
is to represent a system or a model in
terms of nodes and edges and exactly
what those nodes and edges are matters a
lot and in this diagram we had the
parable of Bob and Alice who brushed
their teeth at a similar time because
people in that region just happen to do
so
and we discussed how the statistical
connections
between their activities in terms of the
functional and effective connectivity
are not the same as what is touching
what in the real world
and this
very straightforward deflationary
approach to separating the map from the
territory
yep came back again and again and again
it was like we were on the Carousel of
functional and effective connectivity
and the map territory and the math is
not the territory all of those topics
are so Central
because when we're looking at those
generative models we're looking at a
graphical map
not a picture of the territory
and it's easy even when you know
to forget
yeah
and again I I often wonder how because
Daniel reminds me no people vote which
papers we're going to do and sometimes
it's just availability of authors but
the next paper which was 36 could not
have been a better Co
uh
what's the word co-inhabitant the with
with majeed's work it was uh like the
perfect follow-up Matt and Giovanni's uh
work on on modeling ourselves
yep give an overview go for it
uh 36 was the importance of working
backwards
you're the way that you and blue set up
the the entire paper was well we're
going to go to the end and we're going
to come we're going to work our way back
through this paper just so that it makes
sense because I think the there was a
bit of a woo-woo kind of uh sense from
reading the paper because it was very
very deeply philosophical
um also just introduce the claim that in
order for internal representations to be
wiped out we need to marginalize the
unit call in action really radical
as if adding an exclamation point to
your claim somehow changes the
relationship of an action which is a
part to the entirety which is a whole
so you when you guys first picked up the
paper and you're doing the dot zero
um already there was like okay well I
wonder what we're getting into here well
you also asked indirectly how artists
indirectly how artists people with good
external rep who are good external
external representationalists maybe have
a different gapping or way of entangling
or both
the organizational structural and
content related and functional aspects
is either representative or
non-representative within parameters
uh yeah a nice table there set up which
boy you got a lot of shelf life out of
it who is useful for all three live
streams what I found most interesting
was that to be an activist meant to you
the use of simple heuristics means
control mechanisms do not need to get to
the level of sophistication more than
what uh what short catch and long you
had a great diagram of the baseball Carl
hitting it out of the park categorizing
mine the fep equals you can be all over
the map does that mean we can engineer a
bridge to everywhere which was one of
the questions I'd written down actually
after watching you you and blue do the
dot zero then in the dot one how does
transition
go from materialize to non-materialize
and then back and that was
that brought us to the idea of what
stable and what's dynamic juggled as a
process of predictivity
in order for representation and
non-representation to coexist this was
the great thing they are they are
bedfellows Dean and blue debated the
scale freeness and the scale
friendliness of science
I.E observations recordings analysis and
prediction
so modeling ourselves in real time with
Daniel's uh substituting disciplinary
for generalization as modeler strategy
the question was raised around what must
exist pre-plan pre-model and then we I
don't know the lady's name who joined us
for the Danielle Danielle
uh
we got into some really interesting
loops with your um table again we
started we were looking at
organizational structural and content
related has probably more stable things
that we want to Anchor with those edges
and nodes represented and not kind of
moving around all over the place or
without edges you can have a gap like
but there there was a point that came up
was the black lines separating the rows
and the and the um columns
were they solid or were they actual gaps
so that was kind of interesting
um uh and then there was a functional as
radical Dynamic and dependent on those
stabilities
uh now is modeling ourselves how when
where what what if and which if we act
how does that impact the model that we
believe exists as we boundary cross
which again if you take it to the stuff
that vision is talking about on a on an
organizational level that gets real
that's combinatorially explosive so it's
interesting that the how we model
ourselves
has a huge impact on how do we model
ourselves as an organization as a weave
that which we'd like to remain constant
with that which we'd like to see changed
so that was uh modeling ourselves and
again it was Matt and Giovanni didn't
show up but man would have been awesome
to have them there and kind of lead that
circus because it was great it was great
debate between
blue and I because she really wants
science to be seen as it and I really
like science to be seen as specific and
you are the great moderator and said no
it's both so I was 36 bottling ourselves
wow yeah I totally forgot about
Carl hitting it out of the park about
Carl bonds
that is fantastic hitting the particle
out of the park and and about where is
representation oh representation where
art thy staying yeah that was it was too
fun it was too fun and and also just so
people
um know like the live stream page
has the slides for every
um every single live stream that we're
discussing
you can find
um you can find the live stream the
title the paper the transcript the
GitHub where you can contribute to the
journal
as well as the slides so when we're
pulling slides
you can also look at them so yeah this
was 36 was awesome
all right 37 37
free energy a user's guide by Stephen
Francis Mann Ross Payne and Michael
Kirchoff from 2021
you want to take a first pass
well
I just I just remember that uh
as much as I'd like to be able to say I
could do the math
um if somebody else does the math and I
can follow along at my own pace this is
where I learned
um
Jacob's gift basically
so that's what my first pass is I know
what I know when I'm when I'm I'm in the
presence of people who could go a lot
further on that plane than I can so
yeah yeah the the paper
is an Excellence
user's guide or introduction
one memorable section was on this
trilemma or trioelectric of general or
philosophical claims mathematical claims
and empirical claims and they went
through Edge by Edge and they asked
how do claims from each of those three
vertices
justify each other
and so we hear that all the time people
speaking about active inference and
other areas well because the brain is
this way we use this equation or we use
this equation because the brain is this
way or because of this philosophical
belief we use this equation it's like
seeing it laid out that way
brings a huge amount of rigor and it
also helps us understand that rigor is
not just increasingly technical math
rigor includes
the relationships among mathematical
philosophical and empirical claims from
different fields so that was one key
takeaway for me and another was this um
the three piece
the tale of three p's
and it was a focus of the paper to point
to the unconventional way
in which preferences are utilized in
active inference
which is not as a reward or a goal
function
but rather something that is kind of the
fundamental frequency of the generative
model
and so you have entities
striving to return to the bottom of the
bowl
in terms of the path of least action in
terms of the frequency that they want to
be at and that is the embodiment of
preference and as we came to see later
homeostasis and allostasis
but there isn't some sort of dual track
between what is and what should be
rather there's a bowl that represents
what could be and is and should be
through its shape and it's about the
ball moving on that shape by which
preferences come to be enacted
so that was something that was pointed
to and very approachable and they talked
a lot about how they situated the
audience of the work in terms of wanting
to speak to philosophers who really did
want to learn about what free energy
principle is about
one of the things that I got kind of
reinforced in my mind is because I I
kind of believe that Friars are on one
side of a Markov blanket and priorities
are on another what that Tale of Three
P's kind of in my head
gave me a little bit of
latitude on was preferences can be on
either side of the blanket they can
literally cross through they can they
can pair out preferences can pair up
with your priors you can figure out what
those things are that have been sort of
burnt into your your neuro Nero
desire lines and they can also
preferences can also be working with
with your your priorities in this moment
right as you find yourself now okay this
is what the niches the information the
niche is sharing with me but
what's my priority what's my preference
as well so that was what the the three
piece thing I remember now when we were
talking about that's going oh okay
don't get the three things mixed up give
each one of them their their time in the
spotlight
um all right live stream 38. was
evolution of brain architectures for
predictive coding and active inference
by Giovanni pizzullo Thomas Parr Carl
fursten from December 2021.
and the topic here is so important
what is the evolutionary
neurophysiological basis of cognition
and how to complex cognitive phenotypes
arise
at a developmental time scale at an
ecological time scale in an evolutionary
time scale
and where this paper eventually
takes us
is into thinking about the graphical
models again remember what we discussed
just a few slides ago about graphical
models
the graphical models which enable or
facilitate or underlie different kinds
of functional outcomes and then how
structural modification on graphical
model architectures
enable different traits
to emerge diverge duplicate and innovate
and so here we see on the right side
it's a a tree of options starting from a
relatively simple initial graphical
model how different kinds of
modifications duplications
Etc can result in the kinds of
functional as well as structural
phenomena that we observe in living
creatures today and whether that's the
redundancy of Gene regulatory networks
or the paralyzed architecture of the
mammalian cortex these are the kinds of
phenomena that this paper set out to
bridge the gap with between simply
representing things as they are as
graphical models and understanding what
if you weren't just studying the ant
brain today but what if you were
studying the amp brain
over its phylogenetic history how would
those generative models be changing
how do things like temporal depth or
Intermodal Fusion come into play and so
that was a nice paper that connects to
Evolution and a bunch of other
behavioral areas
really helped me understand or confirmed
in my mind that there's a big difference
between a person who makes a model and
somebody who has to interpret somebody's
third party model because I remember
going through this I was I felt like I
was learning on the Fly because even as
I was reading the paper there was a lot
there to try to parse and just having to
be able to converse with you in blue and
I think Stephen was a part of this one
as well for a bit of time
um
it made it a lot easier for me to kind
of understand As an interpreter of
models as opposed to somebody who's
here's my model what do you think of it
it was taking some of these really
complicated models that other people
have designed and then trying to put
make it into something that I had
adopted
nice
okay live stream 39 morphogenesis as
Bayesian inference a variational
approach to pattern formation and
control and complex biological systems
by Franz kuchly and Carl friston Georgie
georgiev and Michael Levin
this paper
took what in many other situations are a
mathematics of structurally stable
but dynamically signaling architectures
like the brain
and considered the case of structurally
volatile
dynamically signaling structures and so
they focused on one of the key model
systems in the Levin lab which is the
planarian morphogenesis
and
upon cutting this animal
it quickly reforms
into
a self-similar body plan so that has
implications that are being developed in
a whole host of areas related to health
and development and disease
and the paper uses a
a somewhat technical variational
Bayesian
mathematics
which we also jumped into and we had
Franz join us
here
in the office overlooking some gray
featureless landscape
and had just incredible
um insights to share
and we talked about the environment what
our developmental priors and
trajectories what are preferences over
morphologies and this really opened up
the discussion
from as mentioned at the beginning
systems that have a structural stasis
that do signaling in that structural
stasis like all the computers are hooked
up and now they're talking to each other
but they're hooked up the way they're
hooked up well what if the computers can
change how they're hooked up or what if
they're moving around that is another
space that also connects us to a lot of
the physics of the embodied worlds maybe
there's friction maybe there's viscosity
maybe there's
um
a razor that splits two halves from each
other and um
it was a great discussion to see how the
mathematics of the variational Bayesian
approach is able to accommodate
these different focal systems which
speaks to the generalizability of active
inference
there are a lot of formalisms there but
it didn't feel normal talking with Frank
and it just felt like
um
the possible with regeneration we had
had a whole bunch of fields that yet to
be explored and the kind of openness
thinking openness that that
opens up possibility was really that was
really cool about that live stream set
awesome all right
40. who could forget
a free energy principle for generic
Quantum systems
2021 paper in fact a year and a day ago
by Chris Fields Carl friston James
glazebrook and Michael Levin so this
paper
um
we needed to situate ourself
on one hand here represented as the
x-axis
sometimes we find ourselves going back
and forth between more talking about
free energy principle and active
inference other times
discussing literature or ideas that are
outside of the free energy principle and
then orthogonally we can think about
this Continuum between not Quantum and
Quantum perspectives from physics and we
were in the upper right quadrant
or another way of saying that is we were
everywhere because we were Quantum and
non-quantum and we were in fep we had
the authors join for both
of the streams the 40.1 and 40.2
so here we are with blue and Steven us
and and the authors
and
every
sequence of symbols that these fellows
added
was immense
and to be able
to make that
Daredevil jump across the Grand Canyon
and connect the most advanced
perspectives on quantum mechanics
quantum physics Quantum computation
unconventional computation more broadly
today
for example thinking about the
perception action and memory phenomena
in terms of repeated measurements of a
Quantum Observer with their reference
frame and looking at the holograph
it was a great and memorable sequence
it it literally materialized the bridge
to everywhere being in that upper right
quadrant which is which is a fascinating
thing because I don't know how you
engineer
Abridged everywhere but you the
possibility means you have to open up to
more than somewhere and I think that
that was again one of those
one of those sets where you're kind of
going am I really doing well you
wouldn't say this but I would say this
am I really doing this am I really
having a conversation am I get do I get
to sit at the same room with people of
this capacity it was really
fantastic and I got to talk to Mike
Levin for
privately after that because uh yeah the
idea of prediction matter expertise
intrigued him so that was very cool
great wow all right carrying through 41
extended active inference constructing
predictive cognition Beyond skulls
by Axel constant Andy Clark Michael
Kirchoff and Carl friston so here we had
[Music]
um
we had the All-Star team
we had blue you and I trust is Like Glue
if you don't have it you won't be able
to stick together
and our team
talked about trust and active inference
models
and I remember this section of the
discussion
where we had two systems the blue and
the orange
and we discussed like what is their
border what is their interface is it
another region but then if it's another
region isn't there a region that borders
that
and what is on the outside of that and
so how does all that connect to Extended
cognitive systems extended relative to
what
and so
this topic of extended inference was
dealt with
thoroughly here
and the mathematics and the applications
of extended cognition
are so promising
I also remember you discussing the
difference between a type of active
versus a passive offloading there's a
difference between somebody writing a
code on a Post-It note that only they
know
so if they look at it later it's like it
helps them remember what they were
thinking of but to somebody else it
doesn't mean anything and it doesn't do
anything as just notes on paper versus
JF creating a robot and sending it into
the environment yes it might still need
recharging and so on so it's not like
it's totally disconnected but it's doing
things actively and that kind of active
passive offloading
and the way that that facilitates our
cognitive goals was very rich discussion
and I I actually being the first author
of this he always to me he's like Majid
he he brings in
the influence and the how long do you
stick with something before you
you no longer
you know can carry something on what is
that what he's he's so he's such a good
explainer of you realize that the
environment is actively inferring you as
much as you are inferring it that's
that's really hard for people to get
their minds wrapped I mean the first
time you hear that you're kind of like
what
but he does such an amazing job of
explaining that it doesn't it doesn't
seem like
people talking about some silly thing
like fairies dancing on the head of a
pin yep you actually I go oh wait a
second you're right it would have to
I would have to the environment would
have to be scrutinizing me as much as
I'm scrutinizing and trying to figure it
out
nice all right 42.
robot navigation as High rock
hierarchical act of inference by
ozankatal Tim verballon tune Vonda melee
Bart Dot and Adam saffron
this paper was an incredible example of
Applied active inference they in this
paper represented the full rainbow
from conceptualizing a generative model
to implementing it and making a robot
that actually enacts that generative
model in a warehouse setting and what
that warehouse setting required from the
generative model was that there was two
levels at which the generative model was
playing out at the higher level which we
were thinking of in terms of strategy
the robot decides where it wants to be
where it prefers to be and where it is
at a lower level which we connected to
tactics
is related to the kinds of bodily moves
that it can engage in it's more movement
affordances and this discussion
facilitated a lot of
um
action
into the math the computation the
embodiment the Robotics and give some of
the clearest
examples of Applied hierarchical
modeling that came back again and again
and again
so that was fun
all right
43.
paper 43 was predictive coding a
theoretical and experimental review by
Baron millage and you'll Seth and
Christopher Buckley
this paper was quite a doozy it was very
mathematical and quite long the
memorable part of this paper to me was
collaborating with Maria on the dot zero
and
Maria's philosophical knowledge with
predictive processing
took us way back
and that was rooting the discussion in
the ancients
and
thinking about World Knowledge
traditions and Kant and helmholtz we
hear a lot more about that kind of 17 18
1900 philosophy time
but this
pulled us temporally back
and helped Bridge
the math of this paper which was
technical to the ways that people have
simply
perceived cognized acted and
thought about the world around them
and then to speak to the math
this paper almost the entire thing
before something like the last several
pages
it's about hierarchical predictive
processing architectures but there's no
action to be found it's just about
inference inference going up and down
priors and observations and prediction
errors all of that and then at the end
oh yeah we're going to be doing
inference on action we're going to be
doing active inference and with that
tiny
Twist of the knife active inference
becomes
and so it's just amazing to see how
purely inferential
architectures
when they're doing inference on action
the consequences of action are taken
into account policy selection is treated
as a formal thing to do inference on
you get active inference
and it really isn't too much more
complex than that
and then just a last point just like we
had the three areas of claims justifying
each other from live stream 37 with the
general claims mathematical and
empirical claims we had another triangle
in 43. so here we had
on the top biological systems and what
they were doing
on the left we had philosophy and
qualitative claims and on the right we
had formal quantitative claims and so we
made another triangle with pretty much
the same three vertices which is
mathematics philosophy and empirical
biological phenomena
now we took another first principles
pass on constructing those three areas
and what are the nodes what are the
edges and how our inference and action
at the heart of all of it
all right
44.
44 was
the Therapeutic Alliance as active
inference the role of Therapeutic Touch
and synchrony from 2022 by so McFarland
Francesco cerritelli Carl friston and
George ESPYs so this paper was awesome
also here from the screenshot of the
event we have Ian tenant with the inner
sense Channel and projects who saw this
paper brought it to our attention said I
want to facilitate this discussion and I
want to connect interception
and the Therapeutic Alliance in a modern
context to active inference and I want
to bring in these awesome
authors and make this a conversation
that really hits home
and so thanks Ian for for joining in and
helping that way the paper focuses on
the Therapeutic Alliance which is like
the clinical
or medical or therapeutic niche it's the
people in the room it's the receptionist
it's the nurses it's the surgeon it's
the physical rehab practitioner it's the
family of the patient it's the patient
themselves it's the physical
surroundings and to be able to very
broadly
discuss that vital setting while
connecting it to Key active inference
topics like generative model synchrony
and so on
as well as to see their delightful
figures
and the way that they represented the
same
um
a bunch of authors joining for both of
the discussions
and
it was a awesome
series
all right
this one
45.
this is what I'd come back from the dead
and this is what I walked into
I knew there is a reason why I wasn't
called away it was because of 45. 45 was
the the free energy principle made
simpler but not too simple by Carl
furston Lancelot DeCosta nor Sajid
Connor Hines Kyle olholtzerver grigorous
padiotis and Thomas Parr
well I think the best way to summarize
or crystallize the experience of this
stream was
blue and I spent many hours preparing
for the dot zero we were having separate
meetings and doing asynchronous work to
really work through and understand the
mathematics of this paper
and we did the 45.0 in May it was all
great we were looking forward to June
um we had invited the authors we didn't
really know what was going to happen and
it was several minutes after the hour
where we were supposed to start and so
we usually just try to start on the hour
or a few minutes after the hour
why wait longer
and we just didn't have anyone else on
stream
so we said all right this is it which we
we floundered through the dot zero
let us swim again into the dot one
yes please Dean I'm sorry but you're not
telling the whole story when when you
are completely out of your niche and you
guys worked so hard to make sure that
you could adapt for this but then you
took that you had the courage and the
strength to literally jump out of the
ocean
into the boat
and then all you wanted was come on it
would be wonderful if somebody could
show up and at least tell us that
jumping out of the ocean was a good
thing to do and then just like that
yeah yeah just a few minutes after we
started come along and say hey how's it
going here catch and release it was so
amazing and I mean you you might may not
believe that it was that big of a deal
but it was and it was amazing yeah just
a few minutes after starting with the
two of us first Carl first enjoined then
several minutes later Thomas joins
so
yes
it was one moment but it spoke to
putting it out there
yeah and being ready
to show up and being ready for others to
show up but also for these two sessions
that both Carl and Thomas joined for
those who want to know about the
mathematics of active inference yeah
there's there's many miles to go with
making it accessible rigorous and
applicable so not to be denied but
if somebody wants to know the absolute
state of the art
these conversations you're hearing it
directly
and the questions and the discourse are
100 approachable so this was just some
of the highest density learning and
um
Higher Learning
it it was an Institute of Higher
Learning at that time if you want it if
you want evidence of a naivete which is
not something you want to remain as all
your life but those moments when you
allow yourself to be naive and how that
can be a feature watch this if you want
to if you want a first step you might
look at going I don't know anything
about active inference just still
you may not understand some of the
things that were discussed and that
doesn't matter what you really will
appreciate is the generosity
yes
great all right 46. so 46 was active
inference models do not contradict folk
Psychology by Ryan Smith Maxwell
ramstead and Alex Kiefer
so
what is there to say
we are folk psychology we are them
and this is also a topic that people
bring up all the time oh preference are
we talking about like that I prefer to
have this happen in my life belief are
we talking about like what it feels like
to believe something
and this paper just absolutely squarely
targets those questions
and
the conclusion is in the title yeah for
the authors
it's not a reification of folk
psychology it's not chapter two on folk
psychology it's not a nullification
it's not a contradiction
it is a non-contradiction right which is
exactly what it sounds like which may
infuriate those on any side of multiple
fences
so
it was a great conversation because the
topic was so directly tangible and
accessible we did want to connect the
math and formalism of active inference
to how people talked about folk
psychology which is just like us day to
day talking about our feelings so that
was an amazing context and also this
sort of fun stream memory was
I used social media to uh communicate
that the dot zero was beginning
I guess on June 14th here and Ryan Smith
just says I don't know if I'm going to
be free later but I'm free now so we had
Ryan in the saddle for the Dodge zero
which was the the first time
the first time we've ever had an author
join and bring that kind of insight into
the dot zero
so it um you know class was held so yeah
we were Court was in session and Ryan
has joined multiple times and and has so
much incredible Clarity on the math and
on the psychology and the applications
of active inference anyone studying his
publication or presentation career can
know that so it was a great conversation
with Ryan and then also um with Alex
Kiefer joining in the subsequent
discussions and um Dean you brought so
many fun
images and motifs
to bear
it was just like it was such a fun house
well here's the thing and again this was
by June right we started in January
trying to figure out
what did the lines between
mean right so is is active inference a
divider is active inference an enveloper
what this paper said was it's not
contradictory to appreciate that it
could be both
that we have a circle you can be inside
with the spokes or you could be outside
and be the the contact service if it's a
divider
it can be on either side of the line but
if it if it is both
then
why would you always feel that you're
doing something wrong by holding up both
right why is both the contradictory
aspect of this which again encouraged me
in my men too I don't care how you want
to do it you can collapse past that but
if you want to get to fractalization
fractalization being the moment that
you're literally in the gap or on the
line or on the boundary right
that's what affords fractalization is
the fact that you don't necessarily go
well that's a contradiction
Hands Clean we're done
no I I have to stick to something
simpler because I just I will not accept
a contradictory space there are times
for absolutisms but there's also what
Ryan was pointing out which is that
maybe that's a feature maybe this this
ability to see both is something we
should just
not you don't have to accept it but what
again counter factual what if you did so
it was really good and then Alex showing
up afterwards kind of playing cleanup it
was really cool yep so that was taking
us to the end of June we then took a few
weeks off
of discussing papers and in that
inter-semester break yeah we came to 47
so I'll let you describe 47.
it was octave inference and abduction
2021 by ativeko pieteren and Majid Benny
and an active Dynamic social cognition
and active inference by anes hippolito
and Thomas Van Ness 2021. yeah well
again again there was I guess there was
an intention on my part to get first of
all muster up the courage because these
people have spent a lot of time putting
these papers together
um but my sense of it was I've got both
eyes open I'm not focused on
instrumentalism
or an action or taking a realist stance
or taking a non-realist stance and yet
there was all of this conversation
around those
things as to which one entails the other
or which one is came first
and all I wanted to do was hold the
papers up side by each and rather than
having people having to defend one side
or the other I wanted to hold it up as
here's two sides to the same coin we're
on the edge of this coin now looking
down on on both
and what does that imply that's
essentially what that was about because
I think at the core or the heart of
prediction matter expertise not just
active inference as something that we
can subjectify but that we can act upon
in formal ways not just informally
that's
that's when you know you've entered the
the you've entered the divide or you're
on the boundary which leaves it up to
you as the person now that's taken up
those coordinates to do things like
we're doing today reflect back on what
got you here
was it one leg or the other right it's
like saying oh well it was my left leg
that got me here well it was but it was
also the right leg so how do you square
that in in you know some of these
debates where
people's like I said they invest a lot
of time and energy and
effort into trying to make sure that
what they're saying is correct
to the point where they almost feel like
they have to defend something because it
narrowly fits and I wouldn't argue
against that but if we're talking about
both scale free and scale scale friendly
which we are I think we've all kind of
accepted that now
um then how does that work in machine
despite the fact that he was not under
under the most
Optimal Health
conditions was super kind showed up and
once again
graced us with
trying to explain some things despite
the fact that I know he wasn't in the in
the best of condition to do that so
again another
um shout out for majeed Benny and his
willingness to go the extra mile yep
and for you in Breaking the one paper
per series speed limit and having us
consider two papers
wholeheartedly so that was completely it
was helpful that's all I was hoping is
that you know it wouldn't be seen as as
being disrespectful because we weren't
giving enough attention over to
something we were actually entertaining
availability with attention again we
were men men doing things and um yep
that was cool yep thank you thank you
communication as socially extended
active inference and ecological approach
to communicative Behavior by ramitison
and Pierre Poirier
this
paper brought together a lot of the
topics that we've mentioned earlier
communication extended cognition social
um and
we had uh you blue and I
with Remy both times
what can you say
Remy's Remy is a great defender of an
action
a fantastic defender of an accident and
he also has partial encapsulation
whether he would have described it as
that or not he is a partial encapsulator
so
there you go
yeah it was um
it was awesome to have him on
and the open-endedness of the
conversation as we
took a look on the social
which can get one lost
from the first moment
and maybe that's not even a bad thing
but we
we lost more than we've ever found
in that niche of exploring And
discussing
all right
getting into the last three papers here
yeah and the reason why I mentioned the
gap between 46 and 47
was because the we came back with a fury
and
we were mad at anyone we were angry but
we were um Furious
and we uh we had some incredible streams
so yeah almost Center
in representing that for me is in live
stream 49
a worked example of the Bayesian
mechanics of classical objects by Dalton
saktiva DeVille
so for this paper
Ali Jacob and our colleague Ander
we met weekly for about two months to
prepare for this discussion
because this
paper and
more generally Dalton at all's advances
in merely 2022.
have transformed the status of active
inference in the free energy principle
if you want to learn more about what
that really means
check out live stream 49.
Ali Jacob and under put in a ton of work
we worked as hard as we could leading up
to the dot zero
and then Dalton
took us on a journey in the dot one and
the dot two
we couldn't have asked for a better
elucidation
or a more
enthralling presentation of Bayesian
physics I really
mean it and
whether you're working in classical
thermodynamic or quantum mechanics or
whether you're not familiar with those
areas
this direction of work and specifically
the presentation
and the answers that Dalton provides and
just the spirit that he brought are our
absolutely memorable
so I'll just give you a little aside
this is the only time on any live stream
ever where instead of playing music when
I'm doing my workout my third lesson my
third lesson
of this the the dot one of 49.1 was
while I was working out because it's
that good
I could act because it had to be my
third listen because the first two
listens I was just like having to pick
my job off the floor but by the third
time I wanted to listen to it a third
time and instead of listening to music I
was listening to you guys work through
this stuff and I was just like this path
integral stuff changes everything
yeah just briefly for the for the
conceptual
here are the three faces of Bayesian
mechanics using a system and a scheme
that's presented in this research and an
earlier research by Dalton and Maxwell
at all
um
one setting
is where a ball is resting on the ground
and it's not moving that is kind of like
a distribution a belief distribution
that's getting new input but it's not
updating it's just getting the exact
information it expects it's not updating
it's not moving in contrast when new
information is provided the prior
updates to the posterior and it moves to
track the mode of the new Optimum so
that's like if you had a a ball on a
staircase then you pulled one stair and
it fell down to the next one and you
pull the next stair and it fell down to
the next one
those both represent taking densities
Over States like preference as a State
observation as a state
states can change through time but they
at any given time are State based
in contrast and that's where we have the
non-equilibrium steady
State Ness density so all the
discussions we had about non-equilibrium
thermodynamics and non-equilibrium
steady States all of that Nest density
discussion is on the states
what some of these recent developments
in path integrals gauge Theory caliber
Theory maximum Cal as well as the Dual
the discovery of Dalton about The
Duality between the constrained maximum
entropy principle and the free energy
principle
when we calculate densities over paths
there does not need to be a Nas
assumption or a discussion of a mode but
you can get path tracking a path of
least action tracking without appealing
to this intermediated Ness
it's only been a few months but there's
so much more to come here
on the mathematics and on the
applications it's just it's incredible
and a year ago
we couldn't have said any of this
so a lot has happened in active
inference but in the 49.0 you'll see us
grappling with the eras
of active inference and fep
and about what phases in epochs and
even now we can acknowledge that we're
in a
post-daltonian era yeah and and it's
funny because I
before hearing this I it almost felt
like you had to go down the vertical and
then across the horizontal and then down
the vertical and then across the
horizontal and then all of a sudden he
introduced the wheels and the bike went
riding down the steps
that's how different
it it it became now that's still a bumpy
ride you have to go quite quickly
to smooth things out right smoothing
right but that's that's essentially how
dramatic it was like it was like
introducing the wheel
yeah
it's only so it's only a wheel right
Wheels within Wheels yeah
all right 50. so in 50 the paper being
discussed I didn't bring it in was um
interception is modeling allostasis as
control
with Eli sanesh and Jordan Thoreau who
are here as well as several other
authors Karen quickly and Lisa Feldman
Barrett maybe some others so what what
would you add on 50.
well just that again you would see that
interception would be its own field and
allostasis as being a separate field and
then there's this lab in somewhere in
Northeast in the United States that's
trying to defield
bring things into a an opportunity to be
integrated and it was fascinating to try
to see how people
address
operationally and formally things that
seem to be pretty messy and hard to
manage when we're talking about things
like we don't have necessarily access to
the information
in a mathematical way it's a it's called
a Feeling
so how do we how do we blend those
things together and again I'll be honest
I was the most skeptical and became a
fanboy after having great conversation
with Jordan and Eli
yep that was a memorable discussions
Eli gave a presentation
that helped us really like lock in
conceptually how they were framing it
and what they did
some of the statistical Transformations
are evergreen
in the sense that there was a capacity
curve
a probability density implied by a
capacity curve and then a responsiveness
that was a log probability density
and now whenever we see one of these we
see all of them right because they're
all just Transformations either PDF to
CDF or log probability densities check
out the stream to learn more
but whenever we see these we can kind of
see all of them when we see one
and
see one thing see multiple things learn
one thing learn multiple things
yeah it was awesome
all right and the final live stream
discussion paper
so this was uh canonical neural networks
perform active inference 2022 paper by
takuya isamura hadiaki shimizaki and
Carl fursten and this was uh
it was a it was a fun and an honor and a
Learning Journey for me I prepared the
dot zero myself which hadn't happened
for a little bit of time by then
um this was just in November and then uh
in both the dot one and the dot two it
was just takuya and I
and the papers
implications
are so stunning
in light of the prevalence of neural
networks and artificial intelligence
machine learning
the paper
supports a claim that was latent within
an earlier research paper by the authors
but they kind of completed the loop in
this paper to really
uh reinforce it that
as per their figure one
every
neural network
canonical neural network listen to the
live stream slash read the paper to
learn more
every neural network in engagement with
the environment through perception
cognition and action
can be understood
using the particular partitioning that
we use in active inference where the
generative process engages the
generative model of an agent also in
terms of perception cognition and action
in fact the training by which agents can
learn
from their own experiences about what to
do in the future
is also analogous as well and here we
see some message passing reflecting that
the discussion was technical
yet asked basic questions
and
everybody who works with neural networks
or knows somebody who does
I'd recommend that they check out this
discussion and paper
because it was a perfect example of like
making the bridge
and here we see like the the Min 2 of
Min twos we see the partition between
the generative model and the generative
process and then two views on that being
juxtaposed
and so now when we see a neural network
we can think that there's a generative
model that might reflect the semantics
of what the neural network does even if
the structure of the neural network is
Arcane and in contrast when we see a
generative model we can imagine that
there are some neural network
architectures with Arcane topologies
that Implement that generative model
and so as we build these rigorous
Bridges
we see more and more
with the same visual input and so that
is really
advancing the field and also again could
not have been said a year ago isn't
building a bridge to everywhere or is it
getting is it moving in that direction
let's go to Reflections oh okay
if we built Bridges to everywhere it's
like paved paradise put up a parking lot
you know we wanted people to be able to
drive all over paradise and park
wherever they wanted
so we paved it we put up a parking lot I
don't think that's what's happening
okay
what is happening
well that's I keep I mean
again I I get the ambition of
trying to take
some statistical models and see where
they might
be inserted in things that are going out
and doing the exploration
see that
um and my where am I here because I
my
continuing attention to active inference
is because I believe it is a
a way
when you're ready it is a way of
generating way more insight way more aha
moments than what I think is a kind of
unidirectional approach
or a hierarchical approach that says
[Music]
um
Mass all this information put it in
synopsize it into your own synthesize it
synopsize it and feed it back to a um
a board or a Review Committee or or
something like that I understand how
that works and why that
serves a certain
agenda or or or intent I think what
active inference test is it opens things
up
so that you do not have a ladder to
climb or at least they haven't invented
a ladder to everywhere
I think that's what it does is it it
creates options and possibilities and
sees things as it could be this it could
be that
so from a humanist standpoint
um
it just makes available it provides
affordances that's kind of at the core
of the work that's being done
what it it it it
enables
the use of things like counter factuals
why that matters why it's just as
important to ask what if as it is to ask
what is
these are all things that I think don't
even have to be stuck in narrative
spaces I think it's it's what you now
can choose
to try and make some sense out of
and I think a lot of times
in order for people to become
Specialists and experts at something
they have to really focus their
attention on something but I think what
active inference says is
the more times you vary your attention
and change your attentional space I.E
make yourself available to ideas and
phenomena that you otherwise would
ignore because you think
it's it doesn't really matter in this
particular moment the more ahas
the more insights you yourself gained so
I don't know that we're Paving over
anything I don't think that the bridge
has to be something positivist and
material in fact
as we talked about at that very
um
second set of live streams this year is
the thing is the hidden State hidden
because of a shroud something that's
material something that blinds us to the
situation or is it simply something that
we just haven't
given our attention to over yet it's it
do I need do I need to um build a bridge
across the Grand Canyon or is seeing
across it to the other side enough
that's what active inference asks us to
explore
um I think if people want to come and
and find an opportunity to socialize
with other people around
references there's work to do that to do
with that around stuff that Bijan has
written about and stuff that Carl has
written about and those are fantastic
exercises but I think there's more to it
than that and I think the everywhere
part is something that again
it gets reinforced when you're putting
on a live stream that you put in hours
and hours and hours of preparation on
and you don't know whether or not the
person who actually was the author of
the work is going to be able to show up
or not because these are busy people and
then they do
that's an active inference moment that's
a kind of a dedication to
a philosophy and I think that's where
Carl said there's a lot of stuff that
still has to be worked out by the
philosophers
well I continue along with Thomas and
Dalton to try to work out what the
formalisms and the operations are so I
think an eye on each is kind of where we
are today there's probably less room for
people to say no it's one or the other
and I think there's a lot more room to
say well if we put this and this and
this together
I wonder what kind of smoothie that
derives
hmm that's my that's my sense of where
we are at the start of 2023.
yes
it
was like
in the beginning of the year
if only we could just
pin it down is active inference realist
or is active inference this way right if
we could just get it on the table
on procrustees bed then
I would be able to approach it I'm too
busy right now I'm too overwhelmed right
now it's too complex right now it's too
ambiguous right now it's changing too
fast right now if you could just
stabilize it in this one dimension right
then I'll meet you and I'll be ready to
talk
and out of that environment
the doorway was dialogue
and getting different perspectives
together
beginner
intermediate and Beyond
today
it is becoming a growing ecosystem of
Education research applications and
service
where it's not just that there can be
the coexistence of different
perspectives it's that there are there
must be and we love that
it seems it seems a bit
counter-intuitive
but the if there is a nature part to
this
one of the things we might Discover at
the end of 2023 that are that there's
more pockets of feral and Wild
behavior and activity
as opposed to less that the more times
people come and say is there a packaged
ver is there a Disneyland version of
this that I can use as my entry point
perhaps what they'll discover is
there's there's an opportunity you know
you when you hit your ball out of bounds
in Costa Rica there's signs that says do
not find your ball
there are scorpions there are snakes oh
and there are crocodiles crocodiles
don't just inhabit the water areas they
literally hang out in the forest and so
you respect that right
unless you unless you're going to
properly protect your your nine iron
Ain't Gonna Save You
is my point but but there's a there's a
there's a piece of this that's that's
highly groomed highly formalized and I
think there's also a piece of this that
from a from a behavioral
active standpoint we might find a year
from now is
a lot more enabling
is a lot more feral is a lot more
who who who wants to go into those
marginal areas and and really poke
around a little bit
and I think again what people might find
is that active inferences into Shield
but it is an anchor it provides the
organizational structural and content
related stabilities
that people can anchor to so that they
can then go out
and play with those edges or the
non-edges
they can function in ways that they
probably didn't imagine if they believed
that active inference was a ladder to
something specific
so again there's a creative side of this
that I think a year from now
again I I know that there's a bunch of
people in business that want to do
capture work around this and there's a
bunch of scientists that want to get
confirmation and I get that I get what
their goals are and I respect them
but I also think there's a creativity
piece to this that's just percolating
just below the surface and that when
it's
given a chance to run its course
it's gonna it it could be amazing
in terms of what people generate
it made me think
a shield is not a sarcophagus
an anchor is not a pillar driven into
the ocean floor
even something that is stabilizing and
defensive
must have a loose tethering and an
optimal grasp
and
if it's better to be stabilized
why not just put the pillar down
like that is One Direction of thought
and
it may be valid locally or at a meso
scale situationally we're not looking to
resolve these questions in the abstract
there may be a case where you do want to
get inside the iron sarcophagus and hide
but when we are
out there figuring
and balancing
that with figuring it out
we need to also
see those two in conversation or in a
dialectic
so it's not like we can just figure it
out
such that we're going to de-risk
and Achieve out there
it's not the work itself it isn't even
interestingly enough the exact
preparation for the work itself out
there
but also if we're only out there
so much happens that we lose valuable
opportunities for pre-flection and
reflection
and we lose those opportunities to
figure things out while the iron is hot
and so we grow and we act infer and we
serve less than we could
which again may not be a bad thing and
maybe no lives are lost for it
but how to
read and speak between the lines
and make sure that the active inference
Institute
is accessible
to all language and mathematical
backgrounds
as our usage of the active inference
ontology and the formalisms becomes
increasingly sophisticated as demands
from industry from professionalized
research and all of these other sectors
become
increasingly intense as well
how will we be able to
provide services to our community and
Niche
that
neither exactly
square with what their priors are
because if it did they could have done
it themselves nor do we want to come
from a different wavelength or planet
where the material
are
failing to make impact because they're
not accessible applicable and rigorous
here's an interesting thing to think
about as as one of the people who's
spent countless hours
growing this this idea
I don't think back in January of this
year you could have
taken the words from majeed where he was
talking about partial encapsulation and
envisioned a direct application to the
idea that
the active inference lab had to be only
partially encapsulated in order for it
to morph into the uh active inference
Institute
these are the things that we upon
reflection can look back and go well we
were talking about it as an idea but
here's an example of where it actually
became true and we couldn't have I
didn't know at the time that the active
inference lab was going to turn into the
Institute that's what actively inferring
allows for
that's what's really fascinating and
again I'll say this if you really want
to learn go through an exercise like you
and I just went through today because it
gives you the opportunity to say oh by
the way if you want some real evidence
without
pre-staging the idea that I want to
prove this I want to prove that there's
a partial encapsulation just live it out
migrate through it
go through that space time come out the
other side look back on it and go wow I
guess what we were talking about uh
uh
11 months and 26 days ago in fact could
turn out to be
pretty prescient
because there's no way we could become
an Institute today if we didn't leave a
Gap open for that possibility
so it's just really interesting again if
you want to if you want active inference
to be
a repeat of what you have already been
habituated to
you can make it that or you can stick
around and kind of go only mackerel it
wasn't just in theory in fact it
materialized in the ways that the theory
said it could not would
and that's the bridge to everywhere
hmm
well
we put up our canonical final slide
thank you Dean
for for this stream and for all of the
others and everyone who came on
if you're listening this far
thank you for your regime of attention
we are looking to make 2023
and years Beyond it
better
and this was a great year so it's no
slight on where we've been
it's just a spiral of developments
any Dimension or Divergence from your
highest preference
is either feedback you can provide the
Institute
or engagement that you can yourself make
happen you want to see a certain kind of
stream happen you want to see another
language other than English you want to
see a different kind of educational
material become accessible
either provided as feedback or let's
figure out how to make it happen with
your engagements
we'll go out there anytime
wow
well
no word can close
the year so we'll just leave it at that
thank you Dean thank you all right until
next time my friend until next time
all right ciao